Guide to the Mitch Snyder papers, 1970-1991 MS2018
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mitch Snyder papers
1970-1991
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Snyder, Mitch
MS2018
3.5 Linear Feet
Mitch Snyder (1943-1990) was a radical Catholic, advocate for the rights of homeless people, and leader of the Community for Creative Non-Violence (CCNV) in Washington, D.C. CCNV began as an anti-war group and became an advocacy group for the homeless. The largest part of the collection, Series I, 1970-1972, concerns Snyder's prison term during which he became a radical Catholic and non-violent social activist. Contains a diary kept by Snyder, correspondence with his sister Roberta Peters and his mother Beatrice Snyder, and Peters' correspondence with parole officials on his behalf. Series II has a few items to show his CCNV activities: correspondence, flyers, articles, legal documents. Series III has a few family papers and photographs.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
[required]
Historical or Biographical Note
Mitch Snyder (1943-1990) is known mostly for his work advocating for the rights of homeless people and specifically as a leader of the Community For Creative Non-Violence (CCNV). CCNV began in the early 1970s as an anti-war group and evolved into an organization that provides food, clothing, shelter, and educational programs for the poor and homeless. Towards his goal of improving the lives of homeless people, Snyder employed non-violent confrontational protest tactics aimed at shocking the public and drawing media attention to this cause. These protest tactics included building occupation, construction of a tent city in Lafayette Park, vandalism, and hunger strikes.
During his time in prison, Snyder converted to Christianity and fully embrace a radical Catholic form of social protest. Snyder served two years in federal prison, 1970-1972, for violating the Dyer Act. While in prison at the Danbury Correctional facility in Danbury Connecticut, he met the radical anti-war Catholic Priest Daniel Berrigan and like Berrigan, Snyder became an outspoken critic of the Vietnam War and the treatment of prisoners in federal correctional facilities. His protest methods included prisoner work strikes and hunger strikes. The political and spiritual conversion he experienced in prison shaped his life.
In 1973, Snyder came to Washington, D.C. to work with CCNV as an anti-war protester. As the Vietnam war ended, CCNV began to administer a soup kitchen, two hospitality houses, and a medical clinic. The goal of CCNV became "... the task of securing adequate, accessible space, offered in an atmosphere of reasonable dignity, for every man, woman, and child in need of shelter." In 1978, Snyder began a hunger strike in an attempt to convince the Holy Trinity Church in Georgetown to divert a portion of the money parishioners raised for building renovations to support the establishment of a homeless shelter. The Church did not make the commitment, but Snyder's hunger strike received media attention and opened the debate on the issue of homelessness in America. During his lifetime Snyder would participate in numerous hunger strikes. Snyder's celebrity as the leading advocate for the homeless reached its zenith in 1986 when Martin Sheen played him in the movie "Samaritan, The Mitch Snyder Story." Mitch Snyder committed suicide in 1990.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection is divided into three series based on chronology. The first and largest series is the material related to Snyder's time in federal prison, 1970-72. The series includes correspondence, legal documents, newspaper articles, and an undated diary kept by Snyder. Using the material within this series a researcher may read Snyder's thoughts about the social protest movement he encountered and embraced while in prison. The letters and notes written by his sister, Roberta Peters, represent her attempts to have Mitch transferred back to the Danbury facility after the prison system moved him following a hunger strike. She also worked for Snyder's release and wrote letters to members of the parole board and sought advice from people in organizations dedicated to improving the lives of prisoners. The series has material that details Snyder's first hunger strike, a method he used during his work for the rights of the homeless in Washington, D.C.
The second series relates to Snyder's life after prison and specifically his work with the Community for Creative Non-Violence (CCNV). CCNV began as an anti-war and education group and became an organization working as an advocate for homeless people. This series has a smaller amount of material and represents a sampling of the issues Snyder promoted and the methods he used to advance the cause of eradicating homelessness in Washington, D.C. As in the first series, this series has correspondence from Snyder to his mother, Beatrice. These letters combined with the letters Snyder sent his mother while in prison may allow a researcher to observe his activities for an extended period of time and gain insight into the motivations for his work.
The third series is a catch-all for material related to Snyder and his family, but not related to his time in prison or his advocacy for the homeless. Documents include a letter to Snyder from the Selective Service regarding his failure to report in 1964, a 1973 action for divorce initiated by his wife, and photographs of his wedding day, his children, and Daniel Berrigan.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Prison, Community for Creative Non-Violence, and Personal and family materials.
Homeless persons; Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Diaries; Community for Creative Non-violence (Washington, D.C.); Snyder, Mitch
- Prison, 1970-1972; MS2018 Series 1; 2.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The material in this series relates to Snyder's time in prison. In 1970, Snyder was convicted of violating the Dyer Act, the interstate transportation of a stolen vehicle. The letters and writings produced by Snyder during this time will allow a researcher to study his exposure to the radical Christian social protest movement that shaped his life. In addition, the material related to his sister's work on his behalf and the legal documents subseries demonstrates the work of people outside of prison advocating for prisoner's rights.
  - Contact note cards: Attorneys, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Contact note cards: Clergy, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Contact note cards: Congressional members, prison attorneys, visitors, organizations, clergy, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Contact note cards: Congressional members, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Contact note cards: Friends and visitors, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contact note cards: Justice Dept. and Bureau of Prisons, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Contact note cards: Organizations, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Contact note cards: Press, employers, professors, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Contact note cards: List of prisons where Mitch served time, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Contact note cards: Religious groups, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Contact note cards: U.S. Board of Parole, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Contact note cards: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Allenwood, PA, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Danbury, CT, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Danbury, CT, 1971 January -March (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Danbury, CT, 1970 November (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Danbury, CT, 1971 May - August (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Danbury, CT, 1972 April 07 - 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: La Tuna TX (and MN), 1970 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Lewisburg, PA, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Lompoc, CA, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: New York, NY, 1971 April (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Springfield, MO, some dated, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Springfield, MO, 1971 October-December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from Snyder to his mother Beatrice: Springfield, MO, 1971 August-September (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from Snyder: Congressman Anderson (TN), 1971 December 14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from Snyder: Norman Carlson, Director of Prisons, 1971 November 28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from Snyder: Shirley Chrisolm, 1971 August (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from Snyder: Robert Peters, Mitch's sister, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Snyder: Various people about article submitted to Ramparts and Liberation, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to Snyder: Daniel Berrigan, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to Snyder: Roberta Peters, Mitch's sister, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence to Snyder: Stephen Rubin, Attorney, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence to Snyder: Various people, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and Marion Shindell, New Haven Committee of Conscience, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people: Rev. Richard McSorley, Georgetown Univ., 1972 February (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people: Rev. Richard Guerrette, Yale Univ., 1972 February (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people: Parole Board, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people: Psychiatric evaluation of Ellen Snyder sent to the Parole Board, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence between Roberta Peters and various people: Peacemakers Ernest Bromley for the Sharing Fund, 1974 January-February (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: To Norman Carlson from various people, 1971 November 29, December 20 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Kenneth Foley, attorney, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: John Phillips, 1971 November 29 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Gerald M. Singer, attorney, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Ellen Snyder to Craig Thompson, November 02, 1970 and Ellen Snyder to John Phillips, December 31, 1971, 1970 November 02, 1971 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Matthew Walsh, Chief Classification and Parole Bureau of Prisons to Ellen Snyder with questionnaire about Mitch, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Diary: Regarding hunger strike, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Diary: Pages 5-14, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Documents: Response to Mitch's request for transfer from Lewisburg to Danbury, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Forms: Sentence computation record; Release; Request for interview by Press; visit from Dan Berrigan, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Legal Papers: Declaration supportive of Mitch, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Legal Papers: United States vs. Mitchell Snyder and Arnold Joe Paster, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Legal Papers: Complaint about disciplinary actions taken against prisoners including Mitch, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Legal Papers: Many plaintiffs vs. Norman Carlson Re: Class action challenging the policy of Federal Bureau of Prisons which prohibits confidential correspondence between federal prisoners and their attorneys, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Legal Papers: Washington Post vs. Norman Carlson and Richard G. Kleindeinst Re: Interview of prisoners denied, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Legal Papers: Many Plaintiffs vs. John Mitchell and Norman Carlson Re: Class action challenging the policy of the Federal Bureau of Prisons which prohibits interviews between news media and inmates, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Legal Papers: Mitchell Snyder vs. John J. Norton (warden at Danbury) Re: Prisoner strike and the prison's response--Snyder placed in intensive treatment unit, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Legal Papers: United States vs. Mitchell Snyder Re: Appellant's reply brief case #26917, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Legal Papers: Mitchell Snyder vs. Norman Carlson and John J. Norton Re: Writ of Habeas Corpus, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper articles:, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Financial notes for Mitch, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Game sent to Mitch, returned by the prison, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Map used for first visit to Danbury, 1970 November 01 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, breakdown of events, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Roberta Peters' notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Mitch's Notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Protest materials: Statement about fast, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Protest materials: Danbury inmates protests against war, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Protest materials: Danbury work strike Mitch's written material, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Protest materials: Danbury work strike, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Protest materials: Danbury inmate grievances, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Protest materials: Prisoner support group, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Protest materials: Protests against Vietnam War, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Writings: Anatomy of a Strike" by Mitch Snyder and John Bach, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Writings: "Using Myself As An Example" by Mitch Snyder, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Writings: "December 25, I Start To Die" by Mitch Snyder, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Writings: "The Liberation of a Prison Tower" by Mitch Snyder, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Writings: "A Prison Letter", 1975 May 03 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Writings: Words Among America poems, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Writings: "On Saying "Screw It" to Minimum Custody" by John M. Bach Allenwood Federal Prison, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Community for Creative Non-Violence and related advocacy for the homeless in America, 1974-1991; MS2018 Series 2; 1 Linear foot
  This material relates to Snyder's work with CCNV including newspaper articles that document his hunger strikes and other protest methods meant to gain the attention of the media in order to promote his work for homeless people. The series includes legal documents, correspondence, handouts and flyers, and publications about the issue of homelessness in America. This material covers the dates 1974-91.
  - Articles: Submitted to Washington Star not published, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Articles: "Hot Topics: Mitch Snyder on the Homeless in America" Public Libraries Sept/Oct, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Articles: Various magazines with articles mentioning Mitch, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: From Mitch to his mother, Beatrice, 1972-1976 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: From Mitch to his mother, Beatrice, 1977-1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: From Mitch to his mother, Beatrice, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: From Mitch on CCNV letterhead, 1986-1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Post card to Mitch from Tinkerbell Derricotte, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: To Mitch from various people, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: To Beatrice Snyder from various people, 1984-1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence:, 1974-1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Handouts and Flyers, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Issues: Corpus Christi Submarine protest about name, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Issues: Holy Trinity Church, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Issues: Homeless Voting Rights, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Issues: National Visitors Center, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Issues: Surplus food at grocery stores and restaurants, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Legal Documents: U.S. vs. Mitch Snyder Re: alleged violation of probation, 1975 April 01 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Legal Documents: D.C. Dept. of Corrections personal property records, canteen order, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Legal Documents: Criminal complaint against Mitch, 1974 April 12 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Legal Documents: U.S. vs. Mitch Snyder, criminal division, traffic branch motion to dismiss, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Legal Documents: Williams vs. Barry, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Legal Documents: CCNV vs. James Earl Reid, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Button, Witness for Peace, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Card with image of Mitch sold by CCNV as fundraiser, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Articles:, 1974-1991 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Protest materials: Political and social protest materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Publications: "A Forced March to Nowhere" CCNV report, 1980 September 01 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Publications: National Coalition for the Homeless "Precious Resources Govt. Owned Housing and the needs of the homeless.", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Speech: SCS/KY symposium on homelessness, 1986 September 25; Series 2; 1 Cassettes (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Marquette University Archives 2017 August 24 (2017.060)
- Personal and family materials, 1959-1981; MS2018 Series 3; 0.5 Linear foot
  This series is material related to the Snyder family including divorce papers for Snyder and his wife Ellen, photographs of his wedding day and his sons. The material covers the dates 1959-81.
  - Mitch High School Credit information, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Letter from Secret Service to Mitch, 1969 June 24 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mitch and Ellen Snyder's divorce, 1973 August 29 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of family members, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Roberta Peters personal materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Red Banner with stickers perhaps made by a child, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Drawings perhaps made by a child, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Horoscope books, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Peace Sabbath sermons, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)